# Miguel Xochicale

Research Associate in Real-time AI-based Ultrasound Imaging School of Biomedical Engineering and Imaging Sciences
Department of Biomedical Engineering

King's College London, UK

■ miguel.xochicale@kcl.ac.uk

★ http://mxochicale.github.io/ · mxochicale

#### Research Interests

My research interests are in real-time and automatic signal and image processing techniques and AI-based fetal biomechanics. I have also experience in areas of Human-Robot Interaction, Movement Variability, Wearables in Medicine, Ultrasound-Guided Interventions, Medical Robotics, and Research Software Engineering. I have passion for real-time AI-based technologies for Healthcare.

#### **EDUCATION**

# Ph.D. in Computer Engineering

Birmingham, UK

The University of Birmingham

Nov 2014 - Nov 2018

Thesis: Nonlinear Analysis to Quantify Movement Variability in Human-Humanoid Interaction.

Supervisors: Professor Chris Baber and Professor Martin Russell

Thesis submission: 26/10/2018. Passed Viva: 11/01/2019. Awarded PhD degree: 12/07/2019.

Links: Thesis: 🚨 Github: 🖶 Website: 🗹

### M.Sc. in Signal Processing

Puebla, México

Sep 2004 – Sep 2006

Institute of Astrophysics, Optics and Electronics (INAOE) Thesis: Design of digital filters with fewer multipliers

Supervisor: Dr. Gordana Jovanovic Dolecek

Links: Thesis: 🖾 Github: 🐱

## Professional Experience

# King's College London Research Associate in Real-time AI-based Ultrasound Imaging

London, UK

Sep 2021 – Present

- PIs: Dr Andrew King and Dr. Alberto Gomez
- I am scientifically contributing to automatic biometric recognition of Electrocardiography ultrasound data using real-time deep learning techniques and frameworks with Python-based and Qt programming languages via GitHub. Additionally, I am leading the preparation of one proceeding and one manuscript in the area of medical imaging with real-time deep learning techniques. All previous activities in collaboration with renowned clinicians and engineers in KCL, University of Oxford and University of Melbourne. See more at ( ).

## King's College London Research Associate in Software and Hardware Engineering

London, UK *Apr 2019 – Aug 2021* 

- PIs: Prof. Tom Vercauteren and Dr. Wenfeng Xia
- I pushed forward the state-of-the-art of Ultrasound-Guidance Interventions where was involved in the development of a needle tip tracking system, real-time ultrasound image processing, quality management system (QMS) for clinical translation of medical devices, and public engagement activities. Similarly, I developed validation experiments with linear stages under Windows and GNU/Linux OSs, designed electronic PCBs and design CAD pieces for 3D printing holders, characterised ultrasonic transducers, operate clinical ultrasound devices and contributing to a Python library via GitHub following QMS. All the previous activities in collaboration with an amazing team of renowned clinicians, engineers, QMS specialists and researchers in KCL and UCL. Additionally, I lead the preparation of one manuscript in a high-impact factor journal. See more at (2).

### INAOE's Robotics Laboratory Research Assistant in Robotics

Puebla, México Feb 2013 – Aug 2013

- Advisor: Dr. Angélica Muñoz Meléndez
- I developed a Human-Robot Interaction application for dancing activities based on a Patrolbot mobile robot and a single three-axial accelerometer. (See documents and code: 🗹).

# Madero University Teaching Lecturer in Mechatronic Engineering

Puebla, México Jan 2012 – Jan 2013

- I proposed and supervised the following students projects: Haptic Referee Glove, Lightmetre and Pychometre Sensors, Smart Irrigation, Persistent Of Vision Bicycle Wheel and a Delta Robot Structure (See documents and code:
- I proposed and designed a Mechatronic Laboratory which includes: (i) a benchmark for laboratories in mechatronics in México and Puebla, (ii) a 3D layout design and (iii) minimal requirements of hardware and software for the laboratory (See documents and layout: 🗷).

INAOE Research Internship in Robotics Puebla, México Sep 2003 – Mar 2004

• I implemented a speed control for a two-degree-of-freedom robot with microcontrollers PIC 16F84 & 16F877 which communicated via RS-232 to LabVIEW's Virtual Instruments.

#### TEACHING AND SUPERVISION EXPERIENCE

King's College London Supervision	London, UK Jan 2020 – Present
Student: Tsz Yan (Goosie) Leung MSc student in Medical Engineering and Physics (Clinical Engineering) Title: "Towards simple and effective ultrasound-guidance procedures" Co-supervisors: A. King and A. Gomez	Feb 2021 – Aug 2022
Student: Thea Bautista M. Eng. in Biomedical Engingeering Title: GAN-based synthetic ultrasound imaging for fetal development Co-supervisors: H. Kerdegari, L. Peralta-Pereira, and R. Aughwane	Oct 2021 – May 2022
Student: Guilherme Gomes de Figueiredo Summer Project: synthetic ultrasound imagining with AI	Jun 2021 – Aug 2021
Student: Amal Hussein Summer Project: Ultrasound-guidance simulator	Jun 2021 – Aug 2021
Student: Alexander Mitton M.Sc. Project: Vibro-tactile stimulator for dystonia research Co-supervisors: C. Bergeles, V. Mcclelland and A. Worley	Jan 2020 – Sep 2020
Teaching Associate	Jan 2020 – Present
<ul> <li>Medical Robotics. Lecturer: Dr. Alejandro Granados</li> <li>Medical Robotics. Lecturer: Dr. Hongbin Liu</li> <li>Medical Robotics. Lecturer: Dr. Christos Bergeles</li> </ul>	Jan 2022 – Apr 2022 Jan 2021 – Apr 2021 Jan 2020 – Apr 2020
The University of Birmingham Teaching Associate	Birmingham, UK Aug 2014 – Apr 2018
<ul> <li>Engineering Maths 2. Lecturers: Prof. Martin Russell, Dr Carl Anthony</li> <li>Engineering Maths 2. Lecturer: Prof. Martin Russell</li> <li>Computing for Engineering. Lecturer: Dr Sridhar Pammu</li> <li>Matlab Laboratories. Lecturer: Dr Edward Tarte</li> <li>Computing for Engineering. Lecturer: Dr Sridhar Pammu</li> <li>Small Embedded Systems. Lecturer: Prof. Chris Baber</li> </ul>	Jan 2018 – Apr2018 Aug 2017 – Dec 2017 Aug 2017 – Dec 2017 Jan 2017 – Apr 2017 Aug 2016 – Dec 2016 Aug 2016 – Dec 2016
Supervision	Jun 2018 – Dec 2018
Student: Dinghuang Zhang M.Sc. Project: Tools for Human-Humanoid Collaboration Co-supervisor: Chris Baber.	
Bilingual Hight School TECMilenio University Teaching Associate	Puebla, México Aug 2013 – Dec 2013
• Information Technology $oldsymbol{\mathbb{Z}}$ , Euclidean Geometry $oldsymbol{\mathbb{Z}}$ , and Microsoft Office Access $oldsymbol{\mathbb{Z}}$	
Universidad Madero Teaching Associate in Mechatronic Eng.	Puebla, México Jan 2012 – Dec 2012

• Fundamentals of Automation 🗹, Industrial Electronics 🖸, Research Projects 🖸, Metrology 🖸, Physics 🖸, and Computer Integrating Manufacturing, and Power Electronics

# Universidad Iberoamericana Puebla Teaching Associate in Electronic Eng.

Puebla, México Jan 2007 – Dec 2011

• Stochastic Processes 🗷, Digital Signal Processing 🖸, and Analog Filters.

# Instituto Tecnológico Superior de Atlixco Teaching Associate in Mechatronic Eng.

Puebla, México Aug 2006 – Jun 2007

- (01/2007 06/2007) Electronics I, Numerical Methods, and Electricity and Magnetism.
- (08/2006 12/2006) Electricity and Magnetism, and Electricity and Industrial Electronics

#### **Publications**

- 1. **M. Xochicale** and C. Baber, "Nonlinear methods to quantify movement variability in human-humanoid interaction activities," Mar. 2021. arXiv: 1810.09249 [eess.SP], Full Manuscript.
- 2. R. Montenegro, E. Corona, D. Badillo-Perez, A. Mandujano, L. Vazquez, D. Cruz, and **M. Xochicale**, "Air4children: Artificial intelligence and robotics for children," in *16th Annual Conference on Human-Robot Interaction (HRI '21)*, Feb. 2021. arXiv: 2103.07637 [cs.R0].
- 3. **M. Xochicale** and C. Baber, "Towards the analysis of movement variability in human-humanoid imitation activities," in *5th International Conference on Human Agent Interaction (HAI '17)*, Bielefeld, Germany, Oct. 2017, Poster Paper.
- 4. **M. Xochicale**, C. Baber, and O. Mourad, "Towards the quantification of human-robot imitation using wearable inertial sensors," in *12th Annual Conference on Human-Robot Interaction (HRI '17)*, Vienna, Austria, Mar. 2017, Poster Paper.
- 5. **M. Xochicale**, C. Baber, and O. Mourad, "Analysis of the movement variability in dance activities using wearable sensors," in *2nd International Symposium on Wearable Robotics* (*WeRob '16*), Segovia, Spain, Oct. 2016, Poster Paper.
- 6. **M. Xochicale**, C. Baber, and O. Mourad, "Understanding movement variability of simplistic gestures using an inertial sensor," in 5th ACM International Symposium on Pervasive Displays (PerDis '16), Oulu, Finland, Jun. 2016, Poster Paper.
- 7. **M. Xochicale** and G. Jovanovic-Dolecek, "A new method for design narrow band lowpass fir filters using a scale function," in *2nd International Conference on Electronic Design (ICED '06)*, Veracruz, Mexico, Nov. 2006, Conference Paper.

#### **Posters**

- 1. **M. Xochicale**, "Open-cortex: A continuous integration framework for open scientific communication," in 1st Conference on Reproducibility, Replicability and Trust in Science (RRTS '20), Cambridge, England (Virtual Conference), Sep. 2020, Poster Abstract.
- 2. **M. Xochicale**, "Quantification of dynamic facial expressions with shannon entropy in human-humanoid interaction," in 1st Symposium on Machine Learning and Dynamical Systems (MLDS '19), London, UK, Feb. 2019, Poster Abstract.

#### Talks

- 1. **M. Xochicale** and C. Baber, "Nonlinear analysis to quantify human movement variability from time-series data," in *neuromatch* 3.0 (*NMC3 '20*), Virtual Conference, Oct. 2020, Presentation Abstract.
- 2. **M. Xochicale**, "Quantifying movement variability with nonlinear dynamics for human-humanoid interaction," in 25th International Conference on Difference Equations and Applications (ICDEA '19), London, UK, Jun. 2019, Slices abstract.
- 3. **M. Xochicale**, "Quantifying the inherent chaos of human movement variability," in 15th Experimental Chaos and Complexity Conference (ECCC '18), Madrid, Spain, Jun. 2018, Presentation Abstract.
- 4. **M. Xochicale** and C. Baber, "Towards the analysis of movement variability for facial expressions with nonlinear dynamics," in *7th Consortium of European Research on Emotion Conference (CERE '18*), Glasgow, Scotland, UK, Apr. 2018, Presentation abstract.

# Grants, Awards and Honours

- King's Public Engagement grant for the project "FETUS: Finding a fETus with an Ultrasound Simulator" led by myself and in collaboration with Fang-Yu Lin and Shu Wang (07/01/2021 07/01/2022)
- Alexander Mitton won the Outstanding Individual Project award for his M.Sc. project, which I was the main supervisor, on designing a wearable, vibrotactile stimulation device for patients with dystonia (15/10/2020)
- King's Health Partners grant for the project "Sensory system abnormalities in childhood dystonia" lead by Verity McClelland and in collaboration with Carlos Seneci (14/04/2020 9/06/2020)

- My work "Towards Healthy Ageing with Humanoid Robots" was selected for a talk at the second forum of Mexican Talent, Innovation Match MX 2017, ☑ ☑ 11/01/2017
- I won the best poster award at the XIV Symposium of Mexican Students in the UK at University of Edinburgh \( \mathbb{L}^2 \)

  16-18/06/2016
- My project of a low-cost robot was selected among 125 applications received from 35 countries and presented at the first international public entrepreneurship program in Mexico (MECATE 2015).
- Ph.D. scholarship by the Mexican National Council on Science and Technology. 11/2014-11/2018
- Markovito's team won the first place at the Mexican Tournament of Robotics 2013 in the category at HOME where I presented a Human-Robot Interaction Dance Demo. 25-27/05/2013
- M.Sc. scholarship by the Mexican National Council on Science and Technology. 09/2004-09/2006

#### **SKILLS**

**Programming** Python[2014-present], R[2013-present], Robot Operating System (ROS)[2016-present], GNU-Octave (or MatLab)[2009-present], LATeX[2006-present], C and C++[2015-present], Processing[2012-present], the shell[2010-present], GNU-emacs[2010-present], vim[2016-present], pandoc[2017-present], open-source enthusiast at GitHub (@mxochicale)[2015-present], and continuous integration and continuous delivery [2019-present].

Tools GNU/Linux Operating System user (e.g. OpenSuse, Debian and Ubuntu)[2005-present] Single-board computers and microcontrollers (e.g. NVIDIA Jetson Nano, RaspberryPi, BeagleBone, Arduino and PIC)[2010-present], Inertial Measurement Units (e.g. calibration, collection and data analysis)[2013-present], Web design (e.g. Github pages, Jekyll)[2015-present], and Graphic design (e.g. Inkscape, GIMP)[2014-present], CAD design (e.g. Autodesk invetor, blender, FreeCAD)[2015-present], Artificial Neural Networks (e.g. PyTorch, and TensorFlow)[2017-present], and 3D printing (e.g., flsun, cura) [2019-present].

**Languages** Spanish[Native], English[Fluent], Chinese[Beginner]

#### Extra Activities

# King's College London Outreach activities and scientific engagement

London, UK

Sep 2019 – Present

- Organising events in the Early Career Researcher Network of the BMEIS 01-01-2021 present.
- Participation in the Westminster Enterprise Week to engage students aged 14-18 to Biomedical Engineering 10-11-2021
- Participant in the STEAM WEEK organised by the City Westminster Council to engage students aged 14-18 to STEAM ¥
   23-03-2021
- Alexandra Lautarescu and I organised the Reproducible, Interpretable, Open, & Transparent Science Club at St Thomas' Hospital
   02-2020 – 06-2020
- For the event In2ScienceUK, I shared my scientific journey to young scientist on how they can become better scientist.

  20-08-2019
- For the New Scientist Live, I showcased software that helps doctors to create 3D models of brain tumors using AI. 09-2019

# University of Birmingham Outreach activities and scientific engagement

Birmingham, UK Aug 2014 – Jun 2018

• Finalist at the Three Minute Thesis Competition 2018. Video: and GitHub: 505-2018

• Research Poster Conference for (2015) (2016) (2016) (2018) (2018) (2018) (2016)

• Demoing Human-Robot Activities at the Undergraduate Open Days. GitHub: 🐱. 2014–2018

• Coordinator of the Science Seminars for the Mexican Society. GitHub: , Website: . 2017–2018

AIR4Children México & UK

- Building Artificial Intelligence and Robotics for Children (air4children) with the purpose of teaching AIR to children for free. Twitter: **y**@air4children GitHub: **⊚**@air4children 2019–Present
- Creation Libre Robotics, a non-profit organization aiming to freely transfer knowledge in Robotics to Mexican children. Website: 

  2013 − 2017

#### Developer of the Website "Machine Learning for México"

México & UK

• GitHub: **₼**, Website: **☑** 2013 – 2018